Today we are going to make a hazelnut
gelato in the Ninja Creamy. Super easy
recipe, but we're going to elevate this
with some hazelnut praline. I get asked
about hazelnut gelato more than most
flavors for some random reason. I don't
know why. Um it's it's quite an easy one
to make, but there are two caveats. One
is to use real hazelnuts into creating a
super smooth hazelnut ice cream or
gelato exceedingly difficult at home
because we need a commercial machine to
make ultra smooth hazelnut butter. Um,
and it's very difficult to do that at
home. So,
hazelnut extract. This is Lauran super
strength creamy hazelnut. Um, last time
I looked, which was a couple of weeks
ago, this was available on Amazon UK and
Amazon France. Uh, it's an American
brand, so you can get it in the US.
Obviously, you can get it here in
Canada, too. So, that's what we're going
to use for the flavor. And we're going
to make hazelnut praline prolene,
depending on where you are in the world.
This is roasted hazelnuts covered in
sugar, blended up to, you know, a semi
smooth paste. It's delicious stuff. So,
let's look at what we need for this
hazelnut gelato. You going to need 567
gram of 10% fat cream. In Canada, this
is half and half. 46 g of skim milk
powder, 5 g of our lauran hazelnut
extract, 124 g of sugar, 4 g of
stabilizer, 5 g of leithin. This
stabilizer is always optional in my
recipes because my solids and recipes
are balanced properly. I will mention if
it's kind of nonoptional because there
have been a couple over the last five
years. And the last thing is to increase
the perceived creaminess. I will talk
about that in another video. If you
don't have it, don't stress about it.
Don't need it. So, let's get everything
weighed out. I am going to use this
today. Ninja Creamy. We're just going to
make one Ninja Creamy Deluxe size batch.
750 g. If you want to do this in a churn
machine, it will turn out beautifully.
Just size it up. Depending on your
machine, 750 grams is a perfect size. If
you need a bigger batch, double it. If
you need to reduce the size of the batch
for a standard ninja creamy, then remove
30% of your mix. It was brought to my
attention in a previous video, actually
might have been last video, that when I
say it's a cream is so and so in the US,
it doesn't mean a lot. And I didn't
really realize that, but it turns out
that things like half and half in the US
can be anywhere from 10.5%.
All the way up to 18%. And the same goes
for heavy cream and coffee cream. And so
what I'm going to do is just start
saying the fat percentage of the cream
that I'm using. And then I'll do a video
on how to adjust all the different
creams down to where you want them to
be. So let's start with our 10% cream.
567 g. Into that, we're going to add our
skim milk powder, which is 46 g,
124 g of sugar.
Into that sugar, we're going to put 3 to
4 g of gua. If gelato should be a little
bit sticky, so I'm going to four. But if
you're unsure, especially if you're
doing cup measurements, bring it back
down to 3 g.
We're also going to add 3 g of lesserin
into here just to help bring everything
together. In these simplified recipes,
it does really make a difference.
If you've got any small lumps of your
less thin, just break them up the back
of a spoon. Now, let's whisk this whole
mix together before we pop it in our
Ninja Creamy tub.
Finally, our hazelnut extract. It's got
such a good flavor. It's It's a really
natural hazelnut flavor. So, we're going
to go straight in with five g. It's
quite a strong extract. Anymore and it's
going to be too strong. So,
let's pour this in our Ninja Creamy
Deluxe container.
In the freezer, this goes overnight
until it's frozen solid.
So, we're going to go with our sugar in
a pan. We're looking for about the same
weight
of sugar to nuts. You can go a little
bit less with sugar, but we want that
flavor in that praline. So, we want a
nice flat surface of that sugar on the
bottom of our pan. And we're going to
get that on the heat and get it browned,
caramelized nicely. You want it
reasonably dark, but not so dark it
becomes bitter. Flash up that
caramelization chart again so you can
see it. But let's get this going. Whilst
our sugar is caramelizing, you can do
praline with pretty much any nut, but
the strength of flavor of the nut is
indicative to a good praline. So, we've
got hazelnut and almond are the two most
common nuts that make praline, but
again, do it with whatever. So, with our
hazelnuts, our roasted hazelnuts on a
pan, we're going to pour over our hot
caramel, try and capture all of those
nuts, and then let it go hard at room
temperature cuz we're going to process
it.
So, with our caramel poured over our
hazelnuts, we can leave that to harden
off completely and go down to room
temperature. Then we're going to blend
it like this. This is going to take at
least five minutes. Don't overheat your
machine. If you have a small one like
me, do it in stages. Let it cool down.
We want this as smooth as we can get it.
So, with that done, we can pop it in a
container and leave that to cool down in
the fridge overnight. We can heat it
back up again when we're ready to use
it. But for now, that's everything. And
we'll come back tomorrow to finish this
off.
Sudden smell of burning coming from this
machine this morning.
Something tells me it is on its way out.
Let's man
texture is perfect
right here is our
praline.
Don't think you could ask for a better
better single spin result than what
we've got. Let's get some dished up.
beautiful hazelnut gelato in the ninja
creamy. Super easy to do using 10%
half and half over here. Um, like I said
previously,
it was mentioned to me that in the US
there is very little standard regarding
cream and that you know things like half
and half can be 10% up to 18%. And so
I'm going to do a video next week about
all about cream. But for now, let's see
how this one turned out.
Beautiful.
Beautiful. Slightly chewy gelato. That's
how it's meant to be. Perfect texture,
ultra smooth. That hazelnut extract from
Lauran is perfect. It just gives you
such a such a more appropriate flavor
for hazelnut ice creams and gelatoes.
Again, you can track it down and and
family in the UK have actually said that
you can get hazelnut extract by other
companies on Amazon UK as well. So,
track it down. The hazelnut praline is
perfect as well.
Such a good combination. When I spun
this up in my tiny little blender, it
actually split. The fat broke away from
the solids.
And ordinarily that would kind of freak
people out because it's very difficult
sometimes to get things like this back
together. But if you all I did was mixed
maybe half a teaspoon 3/4 of a teaspoon
of warm water with 3 g of lesserin.
Mix that together to create an emulsion
and then back in the blender it went.
Allowed to cool down slightly. In goes
the leithin solution. Mixed it back up.
Away it went. Perfect texture.
Actually turned out incredibly smooth.
Much smoother than I thought it would.
So, if your praline split or anything
like that split, don't panic. There
there are easy ways to sort these things
out. So, I'm going to eat this now for
breakfast. It's 10:00 in the morning.
Thanks very much for watching. Don't
forget to like and subscribe. Let me
know in the comments what you want to
see after next week's video. Um, I quite
fancy doing something new, unique,
different, whatever, but only if you
guys want to see it. So, let me know in
the comments what you want to see. Let
me know if you're going to try this one
as well. [music] and I will see you next
week.